Imagine a new developer joins your team on Monday.
They open their laptop and immediately spend two full days installing the IDEs.
Not only this is inefficient,
but it also creates inconsistent and unreliable setup.
What if every developer could start with a fully configured,
perfectly consistent environment in seconds?
That's exactly what we're going to do in this clip. We're
going to get into our Cloud Workstation,
which we already created.
Now, in this Cloud Workstation, which we have created in the previous clip,
I'm going to install a couple of softwares, and I want to
make this as a preconfigured image.
So in the previous clip, we have already installed the Google Cloud CLI.
Now let's add a couple of more.
Let's say clear.
Let's install kubectl. It is installing.
It will take a little time.
Now once this gets installed, I'm going to install another library,
let's say Helm, saying sudo apt‑get install helm,
let's say clear.
Now let's say sudo apt‑get installed terraform.
Now this will install the Terraform.
Now let's add a new file.
And I call it as a Dockerfile.
Now inside this Dockerfile, let me type in one command.
Say here, from asia‑southeast1‑docker.pkg.dev.
So I give that entire information, and now I'm going to create the
image for this saying in the console docker build ‑t dev‑image:v1.
And this will create one image for me.
Now once this image is going to get created,
this image I'm going to push to the artifact repository.
This image creation will take some time.
Once this is ready, we're going to use this image later on to
create a new workstation so that all the new workstations which we
create will have the same exact environment and all these specific
softwares installed on that.
Now you can see that it has been finished successfully.
Let me just clear the screen, and now I want to push this
specific image to the artifact repository.
Now to push this specific image into the artifact repository,
first, let's create an artifact repository.
So I'm saying that gcloud artifacts repositories
create workstation‑images repository.
Now it will ask me that I'm not yet logged in.
So let me just say gcloud auth login so that I will get authenticated.
Now the authentication gets done, let me run the command again.
Now it is creating that specific repository.
Now repository the got created.
Now let's push the image into this repository.
For this, I'm going to use the command docker tag,
and then in that I'm going to give the dev‑image.
So this is also giving me an error of unauthorization.
So let me just do this, saying gcloud auth configure‑docker,
and then I try to add the credentials.
Say yes.
Now let it run one more time,
and now you can see that it did start pushing this
specific image into the artifact repository.
It will take a while to push this entire image.
Once this image pushing gets done,
we are ready to create the workstation using this image.
Now this has been pushed successfully.
Now I go back to my Google Cloud, and here in the terminal, I'm going to type
in the command saying create the workstation configuration.
This time the name is dev‑custom‑config,
and most importantly,
the container image we are providing here is the custom image that we
had created and pushed into the artifact repository.
Now let's say Create.
Now this will create the workstation configuration. And once
this gets done, we start going to create the workstation. Now
our configuration got created.
Now let's create the workstation.
So for that, let me go down to the workstations here.
Under the Workstation configurations, now I can see my dev‑custom‑config.
When I go into my dev‑custom‑config, I can see the cluster name.
And most importantly, under the Container image,
I can see the image that we had pushed into the artifact repository.
Now on the top,
let's create on the workstation, and let's give a name to that workstation wk‑1.
And for this workstation, I'm choosing the configuration which we have created,
that is dev‑custom‑config and say Create.
Now it will take a while for this workstation to get created.
Here it is.
We're going to click here on the three dots and say Start.
It will take a while to start this specific workstation.
Once this gets started,
we go inside this workstation and see that whether it has the Cloud CLI which
we already added is installed automatically there or not.
Now our workstation got started.
Let me log in into this workstation.
Now let me open the terminal.
And inside the terminal,
let me check if our Google CLI is already installed or not.
We can just type in saying gcloud ‑‑version and say Enter. So we can
see that Google Cloud is already installed here.
So we got all of those things installed.
So that's how to bootstrap secure, consistent,
production‑ready development environments using the Cloud Workstations.